R. Elizabeth Johns Papers, 1932-1972
Sophia Smith Collection
R. Elizabeth Johns papers
1932-1972
Johns, Ruth Elizabeth
MS 607
5 boxes (2.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA worker, Social worker, Social reform advocate. Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1932 to 1972. Organization files make up the bulk of the materials, documenting Johns' employment and volunteer work with a variety of liberal religious organizations from the mid-1950s to the early 1970s, for economic, social, and racial justice; her work in the YWCA of Burma-Ceylon in the mid-1950s; a 1966 trip to Asia and Africa while working for the United Church of Christ; and her involvement with the Pan Pacific Southeast Asia Women's Association.
Ruth Elizabeth "Betty" Johns was born September 13, 1911 to Rev. Benjamin Murley and Louise (Powell) Johns in Factoryville, Pennsylvania. Johns attended Wyoming Seminary, a Methodist boarding school in Kingston, Pennsylvania, and earned a B.A. from Goucher College in 1932. After college, Johns spent the summer of 1933 studying educational psychology and secondary education at Harvard, then took a job as a caseworker for the Baltimore Emergency Relief Commission (1933-34) and the Baltimore Family Welfare Association (1934-37). She took a semester's leave in the fall of 1935 to study at the New York School of Social Work. Johns was a Resident Fellow in sociology at Mount Holyoke College from 1937 to 1939, earning an M.A. in 1939. Her thesis was titled "A Changing Philosophy of Social Work." She taught sociology at Antioch College in Yellow Springs, Ohio, from 1939 to 1941.
In 1941 Johns took the job of Executive Director at the University of Minnesota YWCA. She moved to the national YWCA staff in 1943. Headquartered in Boston, Johns worked with college students in the New England region. From her days at Antioch through her years working for the Student YWCA, Johns took advantage of the academic calendar to do further graduate study at various summer schools. Later, she directed summer Leadership Schools for the Student YWCA and led European Study Seminars for the Student YM/YWCA.
Johns went to Burma and Ceylon from July of 1954 to April of 1956 to train YWCA staff. On her return to the U.S., she worked for the YWCA's Foreign Division training YWCA leaders from abroad in social work methods.
In 1961 Johns became Director of publications and training for the Council for Christian Social Action of the United Church of Christ. In this capacity, she edited its monthly magazine, Social Action. Through this work Johns participated in the major social justice activities of the era, including the civil rights movement, the war on poverty, and efforts to stop the war in Vietnam.
In April of 1969 Johns moved to Church Women United where she worked as Director for International Affairs with offices at the Church Center of the United Nations. This effort aimed to expand CWU's educational campaign on behalf of global development efforts and advocate for international justice and peace-keeping.
In addition to these jobs, for many years Johns wrote a column called "New York Report" for The Guardian: a Christian Weekly Journal of Public Affairs, of Bangalore, India. She served as President of Pan Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. for several years in the late 1960s, and was a Trustee of Grace Congregational Church in New York City.
Betty Johns died on July 1, 1971 in New York City.
The R. Elizabeth Johns Papers consist of 2.25 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1932 to 1972. Types of materials include correspondence, conference and meeting files, newsletters, photographs, press releases, programs, reports, newspaper clippings, speeches, subject files, writings, and memorabilia.
Series III. Organizations makes up the bulk of the materials. It contains files on organizations where Johns was employed and for which she volunteered. The materials document the work of a variety of liberal religious organizations from the mid-1950s to the early 1970s working for economic, social, and racial justice, and to end the War in Vietnam. There are extensive materials from Johns's 1966 sabbatical trip to Asia and Africa while she worked for the United Church of Christ. Johns's interest in international relations is documented through her involvement with the Pan Pacific Southeast Asia Women's Association and for the Foreign Division of the YWCA of the U.S.A. The YWCA materials include correspondence, memorabilia, speeches, reports and other items from her work in the YWCA of Burma-Ceylon in the mid-1950s.
Series V. Subject Files includes interesting materials on race relations and various peace activities of the Jeannette Rankin Brigade, 1967-68.
This collection is organized into six series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
SERIES IV. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES
SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The R. Elizabeth Johns Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002. The YWCA received them from Johns's estate in 1978.
Peace movements -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Social justice -- History -- 20th century; Women and religion -- United States -- History; Women and peace -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Young Women's Christian Associations -- History -- Sources; Young Women's Christian Association -- Ceylon -- History -- Sources; Johns, Ruth Elizabeth, 1911-1971; Church Women United -- History -- Sources; United Church of Christ -- History -- Sources
Associated material located in the YWCA USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - General 1943-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Death: memorial gifts and correspondence 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Education
    - Goucher College: paper, "Juvenile Delinquency Areas of Baltimore, 1930"1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Union Theological Seminary, summer school 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Yale Divinity School 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family 1939-68, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs 1955-64, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - General 1949-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Family 1934-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Andrews, Rev. Richard T., Jr. 1964-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Christian Action, New York Chapter
    - General 1958-60 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference 1958-68, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Church Women United (United Council of Church Women/United Church Women)
    - General
      - 1967-69 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1970-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Asia trip 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ecumenical Consultation on the Role of Women in Caribbean DevelopmentJul 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "People Poverty Plenty Discover Plan ACT" Action guide by Elizabeth Johns: guide, correspondence, and research materials1964-65, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Grace Congregational Church, Harlem
    - General 1959-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees 1969-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pan Pacific and South East Asia Women's Association 1967-70, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - United Church of Christ
    - General (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Council for Christian Social Action
      - General 1960-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
      - Action Guides for Racial Justice Now 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Publications Committee 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Twenty-third MeetingJan 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - National Council of Churches, Social Education and Action Section of the Division of Christian Life and Mission 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Sabbatical tour of Asia and Africa, 1966
      - Planning 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - TripJan-Jul (Box 3)
        - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Notes and reports (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Follow-upAug-Nov 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Reference materials
        - Africa (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - India (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Study Conference on Church and Society, Rajpur, IndiaApr 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - U.S. Conference on Church and Society
      - General and follow-up 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Committees 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Photographs 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Planning 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - World Council of Churches, Assembly 1966, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - YWCA, University of Minnesota 1941-43, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - YWCA of the U.S.A.
    - General 1948-70, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - National Student YMCA-YWCA
      - Generalcirca 1946-71 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - European Seminarsummer 1954 (Johns was Director) (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - West Coast Leadership School 1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Foreign Division: Burma-Ceylon
      - General and memorabilia 1954-56, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence 1954-67, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Reference materials 1954-67, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Speeches and reports 1955-56, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - YWCA of the City of New York, Upper Manhattan Branch 1959, 1967-68 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- SERIES IV. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - Speeches 1942-66, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Writings
    - General 1953-68, undated (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Column "New York Report" for The Guardian: a Christian Weekly Journal of Public Affairs, Bangalore, India 1968-71 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES
  - Peace
    - General 1967-71 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Jeannette Rankin Brigade 1967-68 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Race relations 1963-68 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Certificates 1958, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - YWCA of the U.S.A., National Student Council of the YMCA and YWCA: photo album/scrapbook circa 1946-51 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Retirement tributes1968 (Map-case Flat file)